Guide to the Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department Lead Survey Records, 1971-1975 AIS.1990.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department Lead Survey Records
1971-1975
1974-1975
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allegheny County (Pa.). Health Department
AIS.1990.14
28.75 Linear Feet
The Allegheny County Health Department Lead Survey, 1971-1975, was part of a nationwide effort to identify and treat cases of lead poisoning in preschool children and to remove environmental lead hazards from their homes. The Lead Survey records consist of the Administrative series (correspondence within the department and with external agencies, grant applications, records of expenses, notes on department meetings, lead testing procedures, and equipment), the Blood Lead series (individuals' blood lead test results and summaries of the data), and the Environmental Lead Abatement series (lead test results for individual addresses and composite data per region).
Acquisition Information
Gift of Allegheny County Health Department, on October 9, 1991.
Previous Citation
Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department Lead Survey Records, 1971-1975, AIS.1990.14, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
This collection is for statistical use only. Qualified researchers shall make special application in writing to the Head of the Archives Service Center requesting access to the Records of the Allegheny County, Pennsylvania Health Department Childhood Lead Poisoning Prevention Project OR "Requests for use of the records shall be made in writing to the Chief of Biostatistics of the Allegheny County Health Department".
History
The Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department Lead Survey Records span the years 1971 to 1975. It represents an early stage in the ongoing nationwide effort to improve children's well being by eradicating unhealthful amounts of lead in their surroundings and bodies. Although it later became part of the national blood lead survey, Allegheny County's Lead Survey began as a pilot study of a local blighted neighborhood. Tests of the neighborhood's children showed that they had lower levels of lead exposure than their peers in other cities. Health Department officials sought to determine if the relatively low incidence of lead poisoning occurred because health care providers were not looking for it or because the Allegheny County children's lives were somehow different from those of their counterparts in other cities. As explained in the Allegheny County Health Department's March 1, 1972 Lead Poisoning Control Program book (pages 3-4), "These questions concern us, and provide the basis for our interest in establishment of a lead poisoning control project in Allegheny County..." to gain answers and "provide ...effective lead poisoning detection."
The Allegheny County Lead Survey project was performed under the leadership of Dr. Albert H. Brunwasser, with Drs. Penn Lupovic, Roger Juselius, and Richard Moriarty, assisted by Robert Kambic, Janet Bonk, nurses, laboratory personnel, and teams of paraprofessional workers who were recruited from local communities and trained in survey methods. The Health Department continued to assess and document lead levels in children's blood and in their homes through 1975, when funding was discontinued. Although the Braddock, Hill District, Homestead, Homewood-Brushton, North Braddock, North Side-Manchester, Rankin, Turtle Creek Valley, and Wilkinsburg neighborhoods were surveyed, some areas of the County had not been studied at the program's conclusion, and the reason for the lower-than-expected blood lead levels does not appear to have been found.
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Allegheny County, Pa. Health Department Lead Survey date from 1971 to 1975. This collection falls into three main series: Administrative records, Blood Lead data, and Environmental Lead Abatement data.
The Administrative series affords an overview of the entire project through grant applications, correspondence, reports and publications, and notes on environmental lead testing equipment. Blood lead data makes up most of the collection, in amounts varying by year collected, rising to a 1974 peak. The Blood Lead series also includes permission slips, patient records (case files, index cards), and summaries of data. The Environmental Lead Abatement Data includes documentation on individual residences and summaries of this data grouped by census tract, street, and zip code.
All three series make reference to the "N.B.S." This abbreviation stands for the National Bureau of Standards, whose personnel advised the administrators of local blood lead surveys during this period.
Related Material
The following four publications are available through the University Library System: Allegheny County Health Department Lead Based Paint Survey Manual. Pittsburgh, Pa.: Allegheny County Health Department.
Allegheny County Health Department Lead Poisoning Control Program. Pittsburgh, Pa.: Allegheny County Health Department, 1972.
Increased Lead Absorption and Lead Poisoning in Young Children: A Statement by the Center for Disease Control. U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Public Health Service. March 1975.
Lin-Fu, Jane S. Childhood Lead Poisoning…an Eradicable Disease. Reprinted by the U.S. Department of Health Education and Welfare, Health Services and Mental Health Administration, Maternal and Child Health Service, from Children, January-February 1970, No. 1, 2-9.
Allegheny County (Pa.); Lead poisoning -- Research -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Lead -- Toxicology -- Research -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Lead abatement -- Research -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Braddock (Pa.); East Pittsburgh (Pa.); Hill District (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Homestead (Pa.); Homewood (Pittsburgh, Pa.); North Braddock (Pa.); North Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Manchester (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Oakland (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Correspondence; Environment; Government; Surveys (Documents); Questionnaires; Wilkinsburg (Pa.); Turtle Creek (Pa.); Health and medicine; Pitcairn (Pa.); Clairton (Pa.); McKeesport (Pa.); Allegheny County (Pa.). Health Department; United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; Pennsylvania. Bureau of Community Environmental Control; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Code Enforcement Advisory Committee; United States. National Bureau of Standards; Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission; Brunwasser, Albert H.; Juselius, Roger; Bonk, Janet; Kambic, Robert; Lupino, Penn; Moriarty, Richard
- Administrative, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes correspondence, quarterly and monthly reports, publications, grant applications, office management documents (memos, bills for supplies), subject files, and environmental lead abatement documents. The grant applications in Box 3, FF 7-10 provide an overview of the project, as does the Allegheny County Lead Poisoning Control Program publication in Box 3, FF 30, which may be compared to the County's Lead Hazard Procedures and Project Retrospective publication (Box 3, FF 34), and the March 12, 1975 computer-generated ACHD-NBS Report of encoded data in Box 4. Also of interest are Box 1, FF 19 (a May 2, 1975 letter on hemoglobin and blood lead levels) and FF 24 ("Body Lead Kinetics"), which indicate possible alternative analyses for lead survey data.
  - Contracts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-22)
  - Data handling, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Employee-related, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-31)
  - Publicity, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Reports, monthly, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33-46)
  - System for doing quarterly reports, worksheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Reports, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - NBS work estimates and weekly reports, September 1974-January 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reports, quarterly, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
  - Report: NBS progress statement, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Results of meeting with HUD, WBS, ACHD, GSPH, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subject files, undated (Box 2, Folder 9-16)
  - Supplies ordered, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-21)
  - Budget uniform invoices, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Billing from Children's Hospital, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Billing from Clinical Pathology Laboratory, January-December 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24-33)
  - Bills and invoices from Clinical Pathology Laboratory, February-July 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34-39)
  - Lab accounting sheets (pigs' bloods), 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Billing from Iron City University and Towel, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Environmental lead abatement action taken, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Grant applications, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
  - Forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
  - Lead detector use and testing, undated (Box 3, Folder 15-26)
  - Lead paint poisoning control programs, Chicago and Philadelphia, undated (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Legal action taken, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Publications by Allegheny County Health Department, National Bureau of Standards (NBS), Bureau of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW), undated (Box 3, Folder 30-37)
  - Encoded data, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Encoded data-based ACHD-NBS Report, March 12, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Blood Lead, II.
  The bulk of raw data in this series consists of blood lead test results obtained by "micro-atomic absorption techniques (fingerstick)." These are referred to as "Micros" throughout the Lead Survey Collection documents. As stated on page 5 of the Allegheny County Health Department publication Lead Poisoning Control Program (found in box 3, the Administrative Series), these lead test results were interpreted as follows: 45 micrograms per 100 milliliters of whole blood (45 micrograms percent) will be interpreted as indicating exposure, with at least further observation warranted; 65 micrograms percent warrants close medical supervision; and 85 micrograms percent indicates lead poisoning and warrants immediate treatment. (Note: these critical blood-lead levels are of greater magnitude than the levels suggested by the Surgeon General because local experience has shown that an upward adjustment of 5 micrograms percent is necessary when the micro technique is used).
  When lead exposure was noted, "further macro studies" (page 19, Lead Poisoning Control Program) were conducted. These are identified as "Macros" in the Lead Survey Collection. The "Child Health Conferences" mentioned in Box 16 contain appointments with Lead Study nurses to which parents brought their children. The Child Health Conference appointments, held at regional community centers, replaced the home visits made by Lead Study nurses at the beginning of the program. Box 17 consists of case files, and all but one, labeled "Industrial," are for children suffering from lead poisoning. The numbered case files begin with "#0000016", and with "#9000001."
  - Permission slips, alphabetized, undated (Box 5-7)
  - Braddock, cases 1-28, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Combined housing and blood lead tests conducted by CMU students, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Lab and permission slips normal micro, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
  - Office copies normal and abnormal micro, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Lab and permission slips normal micro, January-October 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8-19)
  - Lab copies and permission slips normal micro, August-December 1973 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Lab copies and permissions slips abnormal micro, February-October 1973 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Lab copies and permission slips abnormal micro and abnormal macro class III, January-September 1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Lab copies and permission slips normal macro, February-October 1973 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Office copies normal micro, July-December 1973 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - preschool children not tested, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Federal and lab copies normal micro, January, April-June 1974 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Federal copies initial, normal micro, April-August 1974 (Box 9, Folder 13-20)
  - Federal copies normal micro, May-September 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1-10)
  - Federal copies normal micro ("duplicate forms not listed as duplicate on printouts"), July-September 1974 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Federal copies normal micro, August-December 1974 (Box 10, Folder 12-22)
  - Federal copies normal micro, November-December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Federal copies normal and abnormal micro, September-December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - federal copies repeat micro, September-December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Federal copies normal and abnormal micro, October-December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Lab copies normal micro, January-April 1974 (Box 11, Folder 7-18)
  - Lab copies normal and abnormal micro, January-March 1974 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Federal and lab micro: normal, abnormal, repeat, January-June 1974 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Federal and lab copies normal and abnormal microa and macro, January-April 1974 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Federal and lab copies normal macro, March-July 1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Lab copies Normal micro May 1974, abnormal micro May-June and November 1974, federal and lab copies normal and abnormal macro third quarter 1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Federal copies normal and abnormal macro, October, December 1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Federal copies initial macro, November-December 1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Office copies normal micro, January-March 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7-16)
  - Office copies normal micro, March-December 1974 (Box 13, Folder 1-17)
  - Federal and office copies normal micro, January 1875 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Federal copies normal micro, January-March 1975 (Box 14, Folder 2-12)
  - Federal copies normal micro, February-April 1975 (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
  - Federal copies normal, rescreen, repeat, April-June 1975 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Federal copies abnormal micro (40-49), January 1975 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Federal copies initial and repeat micro, January 1975 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Federal copies initial and repeat abnormals, April-June 1975 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Federal copies micro rescreen, repeat abnormal and macro rescreen, repeat normal, April-May 1975 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Federal copies micro rescreen, repeat normal and macro initial and repeat, June 1975 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - All bloods drawn, 1972/1973 (Box 15, Folder 12-16)
  - All bloods drawn, request numbers 6-9 and 12, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 17-21)
  - All bloods drawn in alphabetical order by name of phlebotomist, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 22-30)
  - Blood leads grouped by neighborhood, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
  - All bloods drawn, request numbers 6-9 and 1291-1614, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 8-12)
  - All bloods drawn in alphabetical order by name of phlebotomist, 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 13-18)
  - Clinical pathology results, March-December 1975 (Box 16, Folder 19-23)
  - Clinic control rosters, 1973-1974 (Box 16, Folder 24-29)
  - Clinic schedules, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - School lead testing, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Child health conferences, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 32-34)
  - Child health conferences, 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 35-48)
  - Case files without case numbers, undated (Box 17, Folder 1-14)
  - Numbered case files: #0000016-0000022, #9000001-9100085, undated (Box 17, Folder 15-96)
- Environmental Lead Abatement, III.
  The Environmental Lead Abatement Data includes evidence of census ranking to select areas to be surveyed, and site surveys of facilities and homes (arranged by census tract, street, zip code, year, and survey team). Box 18 also contains one file on the 1973 Christmas Toy Survey (analysis of lead content of purchased toys) and two files containing analyses of facilities for children, apparently completed at the institutions' request.
  - Census tract ranking for lead sampling, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-5)
  - Survey Areas, McKeesport and North Side, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Surveys of Buildings #1-43 in Hawkins Village, Rankin, Pa., 1973 (Box 18, Folder 7-48)
  - Surveys of Buildings #1-12 in Mapleview Terrace, Braddock, Pa., 1973 (Box 18, Folder 49-60)
  - Surveys of Buildings #1-11 in Prospect Terrace, East Pittsburgh, Pa., 1973 (Box 18, Folder 61-71)
  - Surveys of Talbot Towers Buildings A-E, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 72-76)
  - Macro Survey, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 77)
  - 522 Tenth St., Pitcairn, Pa., 1973 (Box 18, Folder 78)
  - Notes, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 79)
  - Surveys of lead-poisoned children's residences, 1972-1973 (Box 18, Folder 80)
  - Homes surveyed but blood tests refused for resident children, undated (Box 18, Folder 81)
  - Soil and water surveys, June 1973 (Box 18, Folder 82)
  - Surveys grouped by census and zip codes, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 83)
  - Team lead housing reports, tallies, 1974-1975 (Box 18, Folder 84-87)
  - Christmas toy survey, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 88)
  - Public facilities surveys, undated (Box 18, Folder 89-90)
  - Clairton-Blair Heights survey, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 91)
  - Dwelling unit surveys in census tracts #306-371, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
  - Dwelling unit surveys grouped by first letter of street name, A-W,Y,Z, undated (Box 19, Folder 7-32)
  - Mailing materials (appointment cards, envelopes - addressed, not sent), undated (Box 20-23)